I wanted to make this video to comment
on John Joe Rogan's podcast with Jordan
Peterson and Brett Weinstein and in
particular talking about Jordan
Peterson's
part where he talks about the Pareto
distribution and he it's a national
phenomenon when we have a population
working on a problem creating any kind
of outcome it's going to district that
outcomes going to distribute itself
unevenly so the idea of the preeto
distribution is that whatever that
population is the square root of it is
going to produce 50 percent of the
results so if there's a million farmers
a thousand of them are going to produce
half of the field a half of the food
yield if there are ten farmers three of
them are gonna produce half of the of
the food he acts like the more and I
understand why but he acts like the more
people are involved in it the worse it
is and yes in math that is true three is
thirty percent of ten whereas a million
like is one tenth of one percent
thousand is one tenth of one percent of
a million the issue is that those three
people in the ten don't even make it on
the radar in the million so the more
people that are competing the more
people that are part of that
distribution the better the outcome is
going to be which means it takes a
million people to create those thousand
people with the higher yield it takes
ten people to create the three people so
the more people we have on the field
competing the higher the bar is going to
be set to be part of that square root
and so to say that that person then gets
all of the spoils of everything and they
get to have a better outcome at the
beginning of the next round is what
capitalism does capitalism isn't
responsible for the pre dough
distribution but it is responsible for
the gross inequality in the power and
authority that you get because you have
a higher competency in a different video
Jordan talks about this coin flip game
where you flip a coin if you lose you
give someone your dollar and then at the
end one person has all the money that's
not the pre distribution Peter
sturbation would be you have thousand
people in a room you flip everyone gets
to participate in ten rounds and at the
end how many of them had ten tails those
people are the winner how many had Ted
ten heads those people are the absolute
loser they weren't better people in fact
it's just as hard to get ten tails as it
is to get ten heads but we've created
the game in a way that it's unfair like
everyone has an equal chance of being
that one person but then once they get
that position we say that they earned it
we say that that is exactly it took a
thousand people to to be part of that to
have the chance of one person being able
to get all heads and so the more we're
able to make society fair the more were
able to create a foundation of our needs
being met the more people that are to
play the game the more people have
access to musical instruments the more
likely they are to be the best composer
sorry they're not more likely to be the
best composer but society's more likely
to create a better and better composer
and so making sure everybody's needs are
met means owning that pre distribution
shouldn't give you obscene wealth you
already won
you already got to be the best composer
you're already that one that that
thousand in the million so why should
you also get all of the resources there
are some places where you're - where
your competency is rewarded in other
places where your competency is not
rewarded if you would be the best brain
surgeon and get lots of money but
instead Society has decided that we're
going to prop you would also be a great
NBA player so you're gonna be in an end
you're gonna be an NBA star the chances
of that person be the best in both of
those is very small but if we're having
them in the NBA instead of saving
people's lives in brain surgery that
doesn't work if people are choosing
where they're going based on the market
instead of where is your competency the
highest where do you like doing the work
do you want to be a brain surgeon or do
you want to play basketball whichever
one you want to do is probably the one
that you should be focusing on not
Society deciding which one is
and they might choose the NBA in which
case but if the NBA pays better and it
does they're gonna choose that one and
so it doesn't create the best outcomes
just because we reward those with the
highest competency in fact the more
people we have plane that the higher
that bar is gonna be so like I said the
three doesn't even make it on the radar
the three out of the ten doesn't make it
on the radar and the thousand out of a
million and so the more we can get
everybody's needs nets across the board
the more people we have plane and
therefore the better the outcome the
more innovation there is in order to do
that we have to acknowledge a little bit
that being the most competent mostly
comes from luck lack of genetics lack of
circumstance luck of what what forces
the market happens to be rewarding at
that time period and so just like we
wouldn't look at somebody who did ten
tails in a row as being a better human
being just because you're the top brain
surgeon doesn't make you a better human
being us tearing you down and not
letting in practice brain surgery does
it make sense but neither just saying
that you're the only one who gets to
practice you're the only one who gets to
do it and only the top people from the
top rich families gets to go to school
and try to see if they could be a good
brain surgeon we're not getting our best
brain surgeons then and so the outcome
of this he talks about later and I don't
want to go too long but he that we that
people conflate power and competency and
authority he's conflating it competency
falls along this scale power correlates
with that because that like you Joe
Rogan and the more 1.2 billion people he
has on downloading his podcast of course
he's gonna have more reach in more voice
at the same time then giving him
authority based on that then letting him
create laws and letting him game the
system so he has an advantage in the
future rounds him getting to decide
where he spends all that money and
therefore having all of that authority
already having that power that's the
uneven part we're taking away people's
heeere's wouldn't be fair he's doing a
good job at that we want him to be doing
his thing and doing his thing that is
high competency
but giving him giving him more power
gaming the system so he has more and he
has more authority is what breaks it and
we can create a world that works for
everyone where we're helping people find
their their highest competency so that
we get there the highest competency
there's more people playing music more
people playing sports more people doing
brain surgery more people going to
school for brain surgery to find out
who's the best you can do you could
actually do the brain surgery and so a
better world is on its way please like
and subscribe see you later